Guide to the Spy Hop Productions independent film collection 2000-2009
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
- Spy Hop shorts, 2002-2003 Spring; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 6)
  - "Home Under the Range" - claymation, 2002 (Video 3)
    City mice move to the desert where they encounter the locals. When the city mice realize their TV antenna didn't survive the move, the son of the city mice and the daughter of the desert mice work out a solution to unite their families by connecting their burrows and sharing a TV.
  - "The Good Stuff" - documentary, 2002 (Video 4)
  - "The Crocodile Hunter and Friends" - Jarrett and Jen's claymation class, 2002 (Video 5)
    Steve, the star of the wildlife show "Crocodile Hunter", is recreated as a claymation figure along with a pet crocodile and his dog.
  - "The Food Fight" - Jarrett and Jen's claymation class, 2002 (Video 6)
    Two dinner companions argue over supper and start a food fight when one of them tries to force the other to eat the meal when he doesn't wish to ending with the discovery that dinner isn't so unpalatable after all.
  - "Cat's Surprise" - Jarrett and Jen's claymation class, 2002 (Video 7)
    A cat cries when he believes his friends forgot his birthday. When he follows a ball of yarn to a tree house he discovers his friends were merely lying in wait to throw him a surprise party.
  - "Chicken and Octopus" - Jarrett and Jen's claymation class, 2002 (Video 8)
    An octopus is taken ashore by a chicken that then falls back into the sea when it runs into a tree at the edge of a small island.
  - "Leo the Lizard" - Jarrett and Jen's claymation class, 2002 (Video 9)
    Leo the Lizard saves the day when a villainous spider robs the local bank. After capturing the stolen money, Leo vanquishes his foe.
  - "Clean Habit" - Amy's advanced video class, 2002 (Video 10)
    An older woman repeatedly cleans a bathroom with meticulous attention until she is arrested.
  - "Sad Life" - Amy's advanced video class, 2002 (Video 11)
    Amy, a single mother, regrets the lack of attention she paid her son which ultimately ended in his death behind with wheel while driving while intoxicated.
  - "Jack's Recycling Movie" - Amy's advanced video class, 2002 (Video 12)
    Three adolescents discover the importance of recycling aluminum cans and paper cups.
  - "Black Milk" - Amy's advanced video class, 2002 (Video 13)
    A German poem entitled "Black Milk" is read as images, in an experimental film fashion, show hands unwinding a spool of thread, silver ball bearings spinning into a hole, cars and street cars, as well as various other objects.
  - "The Princess and the Pokemon" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 14)
  - "The Rolling Head" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 15)
  - "Godzilla v. King Kong" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 16)
  - "A Dog" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 17)
  - "A Rumble in the Jungle" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 18)
  - "The Big Concert" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 19)
  - "Another Dog" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 20)
  - "Snail Trail" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 21)
  - "Crazy Clouds" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2002 (Video 22)
  - "Crazy Clouds" - Steve's Bennion Elementary claymation: claymation mania, 2003 (Video 23)
    Three animals travel through the land seeking treasure until they find it.
  - "One of the Greatest Magic Carpet Rides Ever" - Steve's Bennion Elementary claymation: claymation mania, 2003 (Video 24)
    Three friends travel through the skies on a magic carpet.
  - "Fair Warning" - Steve's Bennion Elementary claymation: claymation mania, 2003 (Video 25)
    An experimental film short in which a boy enters a bus and as he passes the bus' other occupants, looks into their eyes to see what they are thinking about as a sort of window into each of their souls.
  - "The Champ" - Steve's Bennion Elementary claymation: claymation mania, 2003 (Video 25)
    Glendale Middle School students create a boxing match between "The Champ" and several challengers who are all defeated in turn when he devours them to defend his title.
  - "...Dr. Death" - AOCE video, 2003 (Video 26)
    A boy awakens in strange surroundings with amnesia only to finally remember that the doctor treating him is the same man who attacked him and thus gave him amnesia.
  - "Falling Daydream" - AOCE video, 2003 (Video 27)
    A boy daydreams during a lecture from his father and is grounded when he refocuses on the lecture he is ignoring.
  - "La Musique" - AOCE video, 2003 (Video 28)
    A visual collage of music studio images of microphones, amps, guitars, and posters of music legends in an experimental film style.
  - "Pickles" - AOCE video, 2003 (Video 29)
    A boy, James, who loves pickles to the extent that he care for them like babies by burping them and tucking them into bed at night, awakes one morning to discover that someone is eating his pickles at night. After hiring his roommate to stand guard over the pickles, the roommate discovers that James is in fact the culprit and has been eating them in his sleep.
  - "T.J.'s Bad Day" - AOCE video, 2003 (Video 30)
    A boy, T.J., begins a bad day including running into his "mortal enemies" and being berated by his "evil" sister when he begins his day after stumbling over an "evil rock."
  - "Who Jacked My Stuff, Yo?" - AOCE video, 2003 (Video 31)
    A mix of live action and stop motion animation involving a Lego figurine who is behind a series of thefts of items such as a cell phone, jacket, guitar, and a framed picture.
  - "Bill and George: The Prequel" - AOCE claymation, 2003 (Video 31)
    Bill and George are fighting again although this episode does not involve a food fight. After a disagreement about some children running in Bill's home, George takes offense and leaves with the kids only to find himself the target of Bill's anger once again.
  - "Crazy Fish Movie" - AOCE claymation, 2003 (Video 32)
    Three evil fish attempt to destroy the world only to have their plans foiled by three other fish (an angel fish, a cat fish, and a crab) who not only rescue the Earth and its inhabitants but protect it from further threat.
  - "Stick's Bad Day" - AOCE claymation, 2003 (Video 33)
    Buddy, Stick's dog, runs away and Stick goes out to search for him. While looking for the dog, Stick is "splatted" and decides to return home to play darts where he is "splatted" once again. Stick then realizes that Buddy is in the park and goes to get him.
  - "Dear John Letter" - Girls in Motion, 2003 (Video 34)
    A young woman writes a "Dear John" letter to her boyfriend when she realizes that her quick infatuation is over while she recalls moments they spent together.
  - "Disconnect" - Girls in Motion, 2003 (Video 35)
    Several young women and a young man wish to be alone and so each seeks solitude within the library for quiet. One young woman dislikes quiet and wishes to fill the quiet day with her music as she pretends she is giving a concert on her piano for the world to hear. Some people are alone but do not wish to be, others are not but wish they too were alone.
  - "Expressions in Movement" - Girls in Motion documentary, 2003 (Video 35)
    Dancers are asked for their definitions of dance. A young ballet dancer, Jenny Rowe, who has been dancing for nine years talks about her opinions about dance versus sports as well as what dance has done for her over the years.
- Spy Hop shorts, 2003 Spring; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 7)
  - "Alien Love" - Glendale Middle School claymation, 2003 (Video 1)
    An alien named Albuquerque is invited to a party by his love interest. When they arrive he discovers the party consists of several of the aliens who teased and tormented him in high school. When a food fight erupts, Albuquerque saves his lady love and together they teach the bullies a lesson.
  - "Lost Lonely Doll & Baby Rock Rocker" - Spy Hop video, 2003 (Video 2)
    A rock and roll couple face trouble when Baby Rock has to go to the studio on business, leaving Lonely Doll feeling abandoned and pining for his return. When he returns all is well again for the happy couple.
  - "Scarlet" - Spy Hop video, 2003 (Video 3)
    Two girls, Mary and Scarlet, find they can get along after all when Scarlet (the popular girl) dismisses the pressure of her crowd of friends to be kind to Mary (the outcast) who acts and looks different from all the other girls. When confronted by her friends about accepting Mary, Scarlet stands up for Mary and the two become close friends.
  - "Sense" - Spy Hop video, 2003 (Video 4)
    An experimental film using colors and textures in a domestic setting: orange carrot, blue furry pillow, green wall, black shoe soles.
  - "Space Worms" - UP START claymation, 2003 (Video 5)
    Worms from space land in someone's living room where they are vacuumed up then shot outside by the vacuum. While outside, a bird swoops from the sky and eats two of the three worms. When the single remaining worm returns to its home planet, it informs its leader that the other two were eaten by the natives. The leader then destroys the Earth.
  - "Attack of the Purple Watermelon" - UP START claymation, 2003 (Video 6)
    A mad scientist transforms a normal watermelon into a dangerous purple watermelon and then places the fruit in the local, unsuspecting, pet shop where it attacks the inhabitants until someone places a normal watermelon next to the purple watermelon which returns it to its natural state.
  - "Kitchen That Comes Alive" - UP START claymation, 2003 (Video 7)
    A mysterious airplane flying over a house drops a toxic powder which causes the house and all of its contents to come alive. Vegetables and appliances alike animate to dance around the kitchen.
  - "The Friend Machine" - UP START, 2003 (Video 8)
    A young girl watches TV alone and unhappy until she picks up a magazine and finds an ad for a friend machine which will allow her to make friends with the pull of a lever. Three to five business days after ordering, her friend machine arrives. After some assembly, she has a friend.
  - "Fighting for Friendship" - UP START, 2003 (Video 9)
    Two little girls, Katie and Amy, bump into each other one day and mix up their backpacks. When Katie tells her dad about the mix up, she asks him to take her to Amy's house to swap backpacks but her father doesn't like the look of the house and turns around. Secretly, Katie calls Amy and they agree to meet at Amy's house. When Amy opens the door the girls "instantly" become best friends. Later that night Amy asks her own father why the two families were feuding but he couldn't remember how the conflict started or why it continued. Amy asks her father if it was OK if she and Katie were friends and Amy's dad gives permission. Meanwhile, Katie asks her father the same thing and also receives a "yes" answer. Katie and Amy play every day.
  - "Formula for Success" - UP START, 2003 (Video 10)
    In a laboratory, a scientist creates a "happy formula" and tests it on himself. After telling a colleague about his success in creating the formula, the colleague then takes a dose. After creating a second batch, he offers it to another person who turns into a train and the scientist goes back to the drawing board to discover an antidote. After curing the boy who turned into a train, the three discuss how to market the drug and go on a campaign where they earn money.
  - "Susie and Her Sisters and the Socks That Stuck" - UP START, 2003 (Video 11)
    A girl named Susie wakes up one morning to discover that her favorite socks, which she wore to bed, will not come off. Her sisters wake up and suggest explanations as to why the socks are stuck on her feet. After attempting to remove their sister's socks, the sisters discover that they are now stuck to their sister's socks. The logically minded of the two sisters suggests that the "sock sister" go around the house to find out what sticks to her and what doesn't then find out why those items that don't stick...don't. They soon discover that anything the sister loves, sticks to her such as her socks, her sisters, and their dog. As soon as the revelation is made, the sisters become unstuck. (Some audio corruption on source material for voice over segments)
  - "Eviloution of Death, Part IV" - UP START, 2003 (Video 12)
    Beginning with the scene of the apes from "2001: Space Odyssey" to represent Earth a million years ago, we skip forward to present day as a monkey listens to rap as it sits in a flower box on a city sidewalk as a group of kids walk by. Following the kids as they make their way to a coffee shop to buy a banana, the monkey then follows them to Spy Hop where it attacks the boy with the banana and two of the other children. When one boy stumbles upon the body of the first boy to be attacked, he and his sister decide to find out "who or what did this." After discovering the monkey was behind the attacks, they kill it and throw the body in the dumpster thinking the ape is dead but after "The End" appears on screen, the monkey pokes its head out of the dumpster.
  - "Dream Come True?" - UP START documentary, 2003 (Video 13)
    Teens attending Highland High School's magnet program for English as a Second Language (ESL), discuss their experiences as students at Highland High School, give their own definitions of the word "refugee," and what the word means to them. The refugee students (particularly those from Somalia) then ask students and teachers what they believe refugees are and what they think about the number of refugee students at Highland High School. Refugee students also discuss peer pressure, acceptance from local students, and the friends and family they left behind when they came to the United States. The refugee students are then followed home to show their homes and to describe their culture, religion, and how those things have been affected since they came to America.
- Spy Hop shorts, 2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 8)
  - "It Began West..." - documentary, 2003 (Video 1)
    Exploring the history of non-Latter-Day Saint immigrants to the Salt Lake Valley, this film looks at various factors pulling immigrants toward relocation in Utah such as the Trans Continental Railroad, mining, and factors in their homelands which lured populations from Jewish, Greek, Hispanic, and various other communities. Due to the fact that the LDS Church discouraged its members from working in the mines, the mining industry was a strongly diverse opportunity center for immigrants not associated with the LDS culture. The emigrant population working in the mines created their own community on the west side of town full of "blue collar" workers. Little now remains of these communities and most of the buildings still standing have been gutted or altered so much that there is little left to show little of the emigrant heritage of those working in the mines, smelting, and factories of that area.
  - "Let Me Be Heard" - documentary, 2003 (Video 2)
    A West Salt Lake City Perspective - Minorities from the west side of Salt Lake City discuss how the unique blend of cultures in the area proves to be "rich soil" for rap artists. Members of Sicc Lake Productions, discuss how living and working in the Salt Lake Valley as rap artists affects them and their music as they discuss issues such as racism, isolation, stereotyping, and censorship in a predominantly Caucasian and religious state but even how minorities who are not black have difficulty making it in the rap side of the music industry.
  - "The Other Side of the Tracks" - documentary, 2003 (Video 3)
    Residents of both the east and west sides of Salt Lake give their opinions about where the division of east and west is located, as well as myths and beliefs about property value, violence, crime, and diversity of the two sides. Residents of the west side give their opinions about the bias of the media's attention to negative incidents in their side of town when crime, in their opinions, is equal on both sides of town. Young adults from both sides of town come together to confront one another's myths about their side of town.
  - "Measure of Success" - Reel Stories documentary, 2003 (Video 4)
    Filmmaker Melissa Mullen takes a journey where her initial pity for local (Salt Lake City) street performers leads her to ask the question "what is success?" Determining after asking several street performers what success is to them, Mullen believes that she is the only one who can measure her own success and that happiness and personal fulfillment are vital in the equation.
  - "Voices Beyond the Barn" - Reel Stories documentary, 2003 (Video 5)
    Animal rescue farm owner, Faith Ching, discusses her views on the mentality of many people today concerning the disposability of animals and of life in general as she tells the story of several of the animals who have made their home on her farm.
  - "Ofa he Lei: The Love of the Lei" - Reel Stories documentary, 2003 (Video 6)
    In reaction to a Jordan School District policy restricting clothing, jewelry, or accessories that are distracting during commencement exercises, the filmmaker expresses his views as well the views of others on the policy, particularly as it pertains to cultural items such as leis.
  - "Me and My Mustache" - Reel Stories documentary, 2003 (Video 7)
    A Vietnam War veteran, John Hinton, tells the story of how he and a fellow pilot made a pact to grow mustaches to help identify them if they were captured or killed in the line of duty and that they would shave off the mustaches when they returned home. Hinton explains that he has never shaved his mustache because his friend was killed in Vietnam and as a memorial to his fellow pilot, he has kept the mustache.
  - "From Somalia to Salt Lake" - Reel Stories documentary, 2003 (Video 8)
    Teen refugee, Mohamed Alinur, from Somalia, the grandson of a former president. Mohamed tells about how he had to learn Arabic when he and his family moved to Egypt and then had to learn English when they then sought asylum in the United States. An English as a Second Language student at Highland High School, Mohamed tells of his experiences as he tries to assimilate into the culture while still retaining his own culture.
  - "Not Just Another Pretty Face" - Reel Stories documentary, 2003 (Video 9)
    Miss Utah pageant contestants and former participants are interviewed about their experiences in pageants, and how their community service projects and their ability to interview are weighted above and beyond their appearance in determining score.
  - "El Otro Lado de America: The Other Side of Salt Lake" - Reel Stories documentary, 2003 (Video 10)
    An illegal emigrant tells his story of how he crossed the boarder into California on foot, was sent back to Mexico three times, and his perseverance, not wishing to die on the trail as so many do every year. After making a home for himself in Dallas, Texas he now sends money home to his family in Mexico.
- Spy Hop shorts, 2003 Summer; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 9)
  - "Elevator Gone Wrong" - claymation, 2003 (Video 1)
    An odd assortment of aliens and talking animals enter an elevator which breaks down, trapping all inside. Three of the passengers use their laser vision to melt through the wall and bring all to safety.
  - "Yellow Submarine" - claymation, 2003 June (Video 2)
    Children recreate the music video for "Yellow Submarine" by the Beatles, acting out the scenes suggested in the lyrics such as a mess hall scene, a band playing, and crew working and living on the submarine.
  - "Yellow Submarine", 2003 June (Video 2)
  - "A Hobo's Life", 2003 (Video 2)
    Three homeless boys as a passerby for money. The passerby hostilely refuses and an argument ensues, catalyzing the three homeless boys to attack and rob the man, making off with his wallet and cell phone. The man who was robbed, then makes his way to the sheriff for help. Meanwhile, another boy mocks some the homeless people when they ask him for money and he too is attacked and robbed. Finally, when the second man seeks the sheriff's aid, the slow-acting sheriff begins his search for the thieving homeless. When the sheriff attack the leader of the homeless, one of the other gives a speech modeled after Martin Luther King's "I Have a Dream" speech. The sheriff then shoots and kills the leader of the homeless gang. The film ends officially at this point but is trailed by a few semi-related skits, "Bums Dancing" and "Frolicking."
  - "Gornaks", 2003 (Video 3)
    Four space crew members sit around a table in their spaceship as they eat when one of the crew members, Jim, bets another, Ryan, that there is intelligent life "out there." Ryan accepts the bet and while they are still sitting around the table eating, their ship is invaded by alien life forms and Jim tells Ryan that he'd better pay up for loosing the bet. The Gornaks who invaded the ship discuss their sinister plans for the abducted crew members but when the crew members are being transported, they fight off the Gornaks but in a retaliation attack by the Gornaks Ryan is killed and the three other crew members vow to avenge his death. After killing the Gornaks and their leader, the remaining crew members then send their ship home. During the credits, the alien Gornaks perform a dance.
  - "Freedom Fries", 2003 (Video 4)
    Two French girls and a French man sit at a cafe table when the man sees a flier advertising travel to the US. When they arrive at the US airport, their culturally-insensitive tour guide takes them to a restaurant where all of French-named items on the menu have been crossed out and the word "French" replaced with "Freedom." So outraged by such an action in addition to the callous treatment they receive from their tour guide, the French tourists beat up their tour guide and leave. After they've left, a note inviting the Americans to come to France falls from the ceiling onto the lap of the tour guide. When the Americans read it, they yell "We're going to Mexico, YEAH!"
  - "The Black Pearl" - claymation, 2003 (Video 5)
    Two pirate scuba divers find a giant pearl. When the diver in the red diving suit reaches for it inside the clam, the clam closes on his arm and rips his arm off. The other diver, in a yellow diving suit, is attacked by a passing shark and looses his arm as well, dying from the incident. The red suited diver then revives and reaches again for the pearl only to have it stolen by an octopus that squirts him with ink, killing him. Finally, the pearl drops from the octopus and lands next to the yellow suit diver's corpse.
  - "Green Hot Dog" - claymation, 2003 (Video 6)
    A man walks by a food stand and sees a green hot dog left unattended. After eating the item, the man turns into a green monster and begins a reign of terror on the city by stepping on cars and kicking them around. Then he sees a donut shop, he is squished by a giant donut on the sign and killed.
  - "Blubber Be Gone" - claymation, 2003 (Video 7)
    An obese man eats as he watches the news. During a commercial break, the man hears an ad for "Blubber Be Gone" and orders it over the phone. The next morning when his package arrives, the man tries it but rather than loosing weight, he gains. Angered by the result, he goes to the manufacturer to lodge a complaint only to be shown the "Take at your own risk" disclaimer.
  - "Blubber Be Gone" - claymation, 2003 (Video 8)
  - "The Kids Next Door Movie Review", 2003 (Video 9)